# MARIANA CHAVES

### Statistician and data scientist

@ marianach16@gmail.com

**J** +33 674280830

Nice, France

**Union Series 2** Costa Rica 16/10/1995

m-chaves.github.io

### **ABOUT ME**

I'm a statistician and data scientist with 7 years of working experience in data modeling, visualization, extraction, and transformation. Recently, I have been researching natural language processing techniques and text models in the context of fallacy detection and classification. I also worked in explainable and interpretable AI. In particular, with prototypebased interpretable neural networks and local interpretable model-agnostic explanations (LIME).

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### Research Engineer

### Inria, France

**2**023 - Present

Research in natural language processing (NLP) focused on models and techniques that utilize argumentation and other text data derived features to identify fallacious arguments in social media and political debate contexts.

### Research internship

#### 13S and Inria, France

**=** 2022

Research on prototype-based interpretable neural networks, other text classification models and NLP techniques applied to the understanding of gender representation in visual media.

### Research internship

### Inria and Laboratoire J.A. Dieudonné of the Université Côte d'Azur, **France**

**2021** 

Research on model agnostic interpretability methods in the ambit of images. More specifically, improving resampling process for local interpretable model-agnostic explanations (LIME).

#### Junior data scientist

### Walmart Supply Chain Analytics USA

**2018 - 2020** 

Directed and developed data analysis projects. Main projects included an anomaly detection system, statistical sampling design, and consumption layer design.

### Data analyst

### **Walmart Supply Chain Analytics USA**

**2017 - 2018** 

Data extraction, transformation, and visualization. Main projects included statistical process control techniques and KPI development.

### Data analyst

### **BAC Credomatic Regional Compliance Management, Costa Rica**

**2016** 

Developed money laundering detection models for five Central American countries.

# **EDUCATION**

### MSc DATA SCIENCE AND ARTIFI-CIAL INTELLIGENCE

#### Université Côte d'Azur (UCA), France

**2**020 - 2022

Honors Graduate (Mention Très Bien)

#### **BACHELOR IN STATISTICS**

### University of Costa Rica (UCR), Costa Rica

**2013 - 2017** 

Honors Graduate

## AWARDS

**Highest GPA among Statistics majors** for three consecutive years: 2013, 2014, 2015.

University of Costa Rica (UCR)

**Honorable Mention: Ninth highest** score on Admission Exam 2012.

University of Costa Rica (UCR)

Honorable Mention: Highest score on Admission Exam 2012.

Technological Institute of Costa Rica (TEC)

### MAIN SKILLS

Python

R LaTeX

SQL

# LANGUAGES

Spanish - C2 (Native) English - C1

Portuguese - C1

French - B2

